<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-21T08:02:24-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Leigh Lawhon</title><subtitle>I am a multifaceted Product Manager with extensive experience in design and development. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Watercolour Portraits</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/artwork/2023/09/01/watercolor-portraits.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watercolour Portraits" /><published>2023-09-01T17:13:27-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-01T17:13:27-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/artwork/2023/09/01/watercolor-portraits</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/artwork/2023/09/01/watercolor-portraits.html"><![CDATA[<p>I have recently switched mediums and now work in watercolour. I build up layers of color and texture to create three-dimensional work that captures the spirit of my models. My work can be found at <a href="https://www.etsy.com/shop/LeighLawhon">my Etsy store</a></p>

<div id="nanogallery2"></div>
<script>
  $("#nanogallery2").nanogallery2({
  // ### gallery settings ###
  thumbnailHeight:  150,
  thumbnailWidth:   150,
  itemsBaseURL:     '/assets/images/',

  // ### gallery content ###
  items: [
      { src: 'model1.jpg', srct: 'model1.jpg' },
      { src: 'shaila1.jpg', srct: 'shaila1.jpg' },
      { src: 'naomi1.png', srct: 'naomi1.png' },

  ]
});
</script>]]></content><author><name>Leigh Lawhon</name></author><category term="artwork" /><category term="Portraits" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This article explains the BARN method, a framework for showcasing your projects.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The B.A.R.N. Framework</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/14/BARN.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The B.A.R.N. Framework" /><published>2023-07-14T17:13:27-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-14T17:13:27-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/14/BARN</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/14/BARN.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1>
<p>Writing about your projects is crucial to giving context for the work. Writing an impactful article requires a structured approach that captures readers’ attention and delivers valuable insights. I use my BARN framework to achieve this goal: Background, Approach, Results, and Next Steps. In this article, we will delve into each element of the BARN framework and explore how it can enhance your writing skills.</p>

<h2 id="background">Background:</h2>
<p>The Background section of an article serves as the foundation, providing context and establishing the relevance of the topic. It sets the stage for readers to understand the problem or subject matter being addressed. To effectively craft this section, consider the following:</p>

<p><strong>1. Hook the readers:</strong> Begin with an engaging hook or anecdote that grabs readers’ attention and piques their curiosity.</p>

<p><strong>2. Problem statement:</strong> Clearly define the problem or questions that your project aims to address. Explain why it is significant and how it relates to the readers’ interests or concerns.</p>

<h2 id="approach">Approach:</h2>
<p>The Approach section outlines the methodology or approach used to investigate the problem or answer the problem statement. It is essential to provide readers with a clear understanding of how the research or analysis was conducted. Consider the following when constructing this section:</p>

<p><strong>1. Methodology:</strong> Describe the research design, data collection methods, and any tools or techniques employed. Ensure your explanation is concise yet comprehensive enough to allow readers to undestand your process.</p>

<p><strong>2. Data analysis:</strong> If applicable, detail the analysis techniques used to interpret the gathered data. This could include statistical methods, qualitative analysis, or any other relevant procedures.</p>

<p><strong>3. Assumptions and limitations:</strong> Acknowledge any assumptions made during the process and highlight the potential limitations. Call out any challenges you faced. This demonstrates transparency and helps readers evaluate the validity of the results.</p>

<h2 id="results">Results:</h2>
<p>The Results section presents the key findings and outcomes of your research or analysis. It is crucial to present this information in a clear and organized manner to facilitate readers’ understanding. Consider the following tips:</p>

<p><strong>1. Summarize findings:</strong> Provide a concise summary of the main findings, focusing on the most important and impactful results.</p>

<p><strong>2. Visual aids:</strong> Utilize charts, graphs, tables, or screenshots to present complex data in a visually appealing and accessible format. This enhances reader comprehension and engagement.</p>

<p><strong>3. Interpretation:</strong> Offer a thoughtful interpretation of the results, highlighting their significance in relation to the problem statement and the existing body of knowledge. Consider addressing unexpected or conflicting findings and proposing potential explanations.</p>

<h2 id="next-steps">Next Steps:</h2>
<p>The Next Steps section outlines potential future directions, implications, or recommendations based on the findings of your article. This section demonstrates your forward-thinking approach and encourages further exploration of the topic. Consider the following aspects:</p>

<p><strong>1. Implications:</strong> Discuss the broader implications of your findings and how they contribute to the field of study or the problem at hand. Consider societal, economic, or practical implications.</p>

<p><strong>2. Recommendations:</strong> Offer recommendations for further research or actions that can be taken based on your results. This could include areas that require additional investigation, potential applications, or suggested policy changes.</p>

<p><strong>3. Conclusion:</strong> Summarize the key points discussed in your article, emphasizing the value and impact of your project.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Mastering the art of writing about your project requires a systematic and well-structured approach. The BARN framework, encompassing Background, Approach, Results, and Next Steps, provides a roadmap for creating engaging and informative articles. By leveraging this framework, you can effectively convey the context, methodology, findings, and future implications of your work, capturing readers’ attention and leaving a lasting impact in your field of expertise. So, pick up your pen or open your word processor, and let the BARN framework guide you on your journey to becoming a skilled and influential article writer.</p>]]></content><author><name>Leigh Lawhon</name></author><category term="article" /><category term="Writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This article explains the BARN method, a framework for showcasing your projects.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Collaborate Games</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/work/2023/07/01/collaborate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Collaborate Games" /><published>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/work/2023/07/01/collaborate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/work/2023/07/01/collaborate.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="background">Background</h2>
<p>In 2019 I was awarded a Department of Education SBIR grant to build an educational board game about collaboration. Though the game would eventually be a series, focusing on different STEM vocations, the first prototype focused on collaboration in tech.</p>

<p>Research shows that the top skill missing from new employees (especially those just out of school) is collaboration. Often students spend their academic career focusing on their own success and grades. When they enter their career, they struggle with shifting to an environment where team success is valued. The aim of the game is to teach students to collaborate and why it’s important.</p>

<h2 id="approach">Approach</h2>
<p>My team and I performed research on and tested multiple prototypes with a local school over a 2-month period. Each session we observed game play and collected qualitative and quantitative data and then iterated on the prototype. One observation was that the tokens were very difficult to put away and therefore not suitable for a classroom setting where time can be limited.</p>

<p>Additionally, curriculum was developed to accompany the game.</p>

<h2 id="results">Results</h2>
<p>At the conclusion on the grant, it was decided not to pursue publishing of the game. I felt there was something missing. The mechanics worked well, and students collaborated, but it lacked and element of excitement and was too didactic.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/collaboratory_old.jpeg" alt="collboratory old" />
<a href="https://youtu.be/vfk5_bkJQFg">Original game promo video</a></p>

<h2 id="next-steps">Next Steps</h2>
<p>In 2023, I reworked the theme of the game. I simplified the game by combining some of the cards and reduced the number of pieces by getting rid of the tokens. Additionally, I decided the base game should be general business.</p>

<p>The product was launched and debuted at the Ed Games Expo, September 19-22, 2023.</p>]]></content><author><name>Leigh Lawhon</name></author><category term="work" /><category term="Games" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This article showcases the game Collaborate and how I build it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Color Theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory-intro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Color Theory" /><published>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory%20intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory-intro.html"><![CDATA[<p>This article is written in three parts. You can find the entire series here:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="">Part 1: Color Limitations</a></li>
  <li><a href="">Part 2: Color and Emotions</a></li>
  <li><a href="">Part 3: Color Paletts</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Leigh Lawhon</name></author><category term="article" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This series of articles explains basic color theory. The first post explores color limitations.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Part 2: Color Theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Part 2: Color Theory" /><published>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory-2.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="color-and-emotions">Color and Emotions</h1>
<p>Mention Thanksgiving to any American and they will paint a picture in their head with gold, orange, red, and brown hues. It will also likely invoke a sense of family, gathering, and thankfulness. Colors, and the emotions we associate with them, are not exclusive. If I were to show you a picture of red roses, a champagne bottle with an orange label and a gold foil box of chocolates, you would see the same colors but perhaps think of a different holiday and a different emotion.</p>

<p>These colors and the emotional meaning behind them are a conglomerate of time, story, memories, culture, and environment. There is no “Official Holiday Color Committee” and though we sometimes treat it as such, there is no “Official Company or Industry Color Committee.” As with holidays, company and industry palettes evolve from culture, story, and environment and those colors have meaning.</p>

<h2 id="color-is-a-language">Color Is a Language</h2>
<p>Color is a language just as English is. I can communicate “health” with words like “strong,” “vibrant,” and “energetic.” I can also communicate “health‘ with the lush, healthy greens of vegetables and
Children learn color signifiers from an early age.
plants, the bright yellows of sunshine, and the trusting blues of authority and cleanliness. You often see the same palettes used in industries and branding, not because they are a standard, but because they communicate a message and an emotion that is common to that industry.</p>

<p>Even within an industry, color meanings can change. Would you be relaxed going into surgery if the protective gowns and masks that doctors wore were bright hazardous yellow or the flaming reds of infection rather than the cold blue of sterilization? If you were visiting your new baby in a nursery at a hospital, would you be more nervous if the nurses wearing the cold blue of sterilization, or the pastel yellow of the sun and the rosy pinks of warm cheeks?</p>

<h2 id="culture-plays-a-role">Culture Plays A Role</h2>
<p>The idea that color has meaning and emotion is not a modern concept. An early exploration of emotion in color comes from the German poet and artist Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, in his 1810 treatise, Theory of Colours. But color and its meaning goes back even further and it varies widely by region and environment.</p>

<p>When I moved to Asia as a child, one of the first things I noticed was how positive and prominent the color red was while the color white was reserved for more somber occasions. Often these more historical meanings come from the availability and value of such colors. Red vermilion, also know as Chinese red, was first synthesized from mercury and sulfur in China in the 8th century.</p>

<p>A similar history envelopes the color purple in western culture. Tyrian purple was dye made from crushed mollusks that was so expensive only royalty could afford it. This economic association lead the color purple to signify royalty and wealth in Western culture to this day. There are many more of these cultural color differences. Therefore, if
you are creating data that will be represented to your colleagues in another country, you may need to consider what message you are really sending. The blog “Information Is Beautiful” has created a brilliant information graphic to help guide you.</p>

<h2 id="questions-to-ask-yourself-when-choosing-color">Questions To Ask Yourself When Choosing Color</h2>
<ol>
  <li>What are others doing and do you want to set yourself apart?</li>
  <li>What additional accent colors can you introduce to change the meaning/message of your design?</li>
  <li>Can you use other attributes of color to modify such as value? A pastel yellow can mean something different than a bright vibrant yellow.</li>
  <li>What are other sources for the meaning of color? a. Commercial (branding, products)
    <ul>
      <li>Religion</li>
      <li>Fashion and textiles</li>
      <li>Cultural events (sports, holidays)</li>
      <li>Geography, industry, and environment f. History</li>
      <li>Signage/transportation/chemical</li>
      <li>Nature</li>
      <li>What colors have personal meaning to my message, brand, or information?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="continued-reading-on-emotion-and-color">Continued Reading on emotion and color:</h2>
<p>http://www.brainpickings.org/index.php/2012/08/17/goethe-theory-of-colours/
http://www.winsornewton.com/resource-centre/product-articles/vermilion-cadmium-red
http://www.livescience.com/33324-purple-roy-al-color.html
http://thelogocompany.net/blog/infographics/psychology-color-logo-design/
http://tympanus.net/codrops/2012/04/03/color-and-emotion-what-does-each-hue-mean/
http://www.color-wheel-pro.com/color-meaning.html
http://www.colorcom.com/research/why-color-matters
http://www.colormatters.com/ http://www.colorsystem.com/</p>]]></content><author><name>Leigh Lawhon</name></author><category term="article" /><category term="Part" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This series of articles explains basic color theory. The second post explores color and emotions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Part 3: Color Theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Part 3: Color Theory" /><published>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory-3.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="tips-for-designing-a-color-palette">Tips for Designing a Color Palette</h1>
<p>In the first two sections of this book, Color Limitations and Color and Emotions, we looked at some interesting facts about color and some of the context around their meaning. This provides tips for choosing a harmonious color palette, that will bring your designs and graphics together. In the next section, we will look at when and why choosing color to separate your design and graphics is important.</p>

<h2 id="create-harmonies">Create Harmonies</h2>
<p>When creating a color palette one option is to create a color harmony. Pick a color, any color. As most of us learned in school, that color has an opposite or complementary color. Red and green, blue and orange, yellow and purple are all complements of each other. These colors are opposite each other on a color wheel. But did you know there are other patterns or color harmonies? Color Tiger’s “Color Harmonies — basic techniques for creating color schemes” article does a nice job of explaining the different harmonies, and tools like their Color Impact 4, Adobe’s Kuler, and Colourlovers’ Copaso all help you create color harmonies.</p>

<h2 id="color-harmonies-from-adobe-illustrator">Color Harmonies from Adobe Illustrator</h2>
<p>Use Tints, Shades, Saturation, Warm and Cool Instead of Additional Colors
Often, when choosing colors for a design or graphic, we are sometimes too quick to jump to a new hue, giving our work a rainbow effect. Instead, consider adjusting a limited color palette of two to three colors by adding white, known as creating tints; adding black, known as creating shades; and adding greys, known as desaturation.
Additionally, you can adjust your colors by moving your colors left or right on the color wheel, which is know as making your colors warmer or cooler. This can be seen in the analogous color harmony above where the main color is in the middle; the warmer colors, or colors that move more toward the reds and oranges, are to its right; and the cooler colors, or colors that move toward blues and greens are to its left.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/adobe_ill.png" alt="Adobe Illustrator" /></p>

<h2 id="remember-to-balance-your-color-with-different-weights">Remember to Balance Your Color with Different Weights</h2>
<p>When designing a color palette, it is good to remember that you should not treat your colors equally.</p>

<p>Remember the typography rule:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“WHEN EVERYTHING IS EMPHASIZED, NOTHING IS EMPHASIZED.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The same applies in color. Make one color your primary color and use the rest to accentuate that color. When in doubt, you can always use the 60-30-10 rule, mentioned in this article by HGTV on interior decorating. Companies such as Ubuntu even use different amounts of the same color palette to communicate differences of emphasis in content, as well as different sub-brands as shown in there branding <a href="http://design.ubuntu.com/brand/colour-palette">here</a>. When you are dealing with many brands such as the case with Adobe you may need to expand your palette beyond a few colors into the rainbow effect, but the color balance principles still apply.</p>

<p>Notice how Adobe’s graphic design-based products, Illustrator and InDesign, are analogous and are pink and orange; the web products, Dreamweaver and Muse, are cool and warm versions of green; the video products, After Effects and PremierPro are a saturated and desaturated version of two violets that are very close; and Photoshop, Adobe’s flagship photography product, is blue. Even though the current branding material has a lot going on you can still identify the key color in the image.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/adobe_packaging.png" alt="Adobe packaging" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Good Artists Borrow, Great Artists Steal.”
—Pablo Picasso</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Why reinvent the color wheel? Good color palettes come from many sources such as interior design, fashion, or nature. Or, if you are using a photographic image with your graphic or page, why not pull your colors from there? Use an eyedropper tool like ColorPick and click around to pick up your favorite colors.
In addition to the great tools already mentioned for creating palettes, try browsing those same sites for palettes created by other colorphiles.</p>

<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://color.adobe.com/trends">Adobe Color</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.colourlovers.com/web/trends/websites">Colour Lovers</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Leigh Lawhon</name></author><category term="article" /><category term="Part" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This series of articles explains basic color theory. The third post explores tips for designing a color palette.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Part 1: Color Theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Part 1: Color Theory" /><published>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/color-theory.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>“Color does not add a pleasant quality to design—it reinforces it.”
— Pierre Bonnard</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="overview">Overview</h1>
<p>The application of color will make or break a brand, website, brochure, logo, or even what we wear on a date or to a business meeting. The same goes for how we present data. The more complex the data, the more important color becomes in guiding the participant through its visualization.
Presenting vast amounts of information in a meaningful and usable manner is increasingly an everyday challenge in many domains. This is especially true when working with health care and life science data. The advancement in sequencing technologies along with their continuously decreasing costs will no doubt result in an even larger surge of incoming data along with an increased need and urgency to easily make sense—and use of this data…earlier.</p>

<p>This article will show how you can improve a user’s experience by apply-
ing certain key color theory principles. Other topics to be reviewed here include the application of color theory to data visualizations, the limitations of color use and the different emotions they may convey to your audience.
You will also find beneficial tips on selecting the right color palettes to provide a professional look and feel for your next project, while maintaining or even improving your audience’s engagement.</p>

<p>Finally, as a combined example of improved user experience in genomic data visualization, this document will revisit the National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI) Genome Wide Association catalog and propose a hybrid semiology approach as an example to increasing usability through the application of color theory and user experience.</p>

<h1 id="color-limitations">Color Limitations</h1>
<p>This section on Color Limitations will address some common drawbacks to using color in your projects. We will also examine common emotional interpretations of color in the Emotion and Color section. Finally, the Designing A Color Palette section will present some useful approaches and tools for building a color palette.</p>

<h2 id="the-visible-spectrum">The Visible Spectrum</h2>
<p>The visible color spectrum is measured in wavelengths and begins with violet at 380 nm and ends with red around 750 nm. This band makes up the full spectrum of what can be seen by the human eye. However, the human eye and the devices we use to capture and reproduce color have limitations when it comes to rendering this spectrum.
<img src="/assets/images/spectrum.png" alt="spectrum" /></p>

<h2 id="color-blindness-and-508-compliance">Color Blindness and 508 Compliance</h2>
<p>The retina has two types of cells that respond to light, rods and cones. Rods pick up on the intensity of light and give
us low light vision. Cones are more specialized and occur in three types, each containing photosensitive proteins that respond to different frequencies of light. When these rods or cones are missing or damaged, an individual is said to suffer from color blindness. Though color blindness is typically classified as a mild disability, it affects many people and can become a severe disadvantage when data is represented with color.</p>

<p>In the DC metro map below, you will see it can be quite difficult for someone with color blindness to follow the subway lines, especially where the Green and Red lines intersect for people with Deuteranopia. To compensate for this, you will notice that the map designers have added labels at the ends of each line, making it possible to identify them without color.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dc_metro.png" alt="dc metro map" /></p>

<p>If you are concerned about how your data is perceived by people with color blindness or need to be 508 compliant, you can check it with one of the many free tools listed at the W3C.</p>

<h2 id="device-color">Device Color</h2>
<p>Device color is another limitation to be aware of. Have you ever taken a photo of a beautiful sunset, only to print it out and see that your masterpiece photo is dull and murky?
Inherent hardware limitations restrict the range
of reproducible colors. Your computer monitor is not able to produce the full color spectrum and printing technology can produceg even less. The equipment we use to capture images, such as scanners and cameras, have their own range of colors they are limited to. In addition to that, all these things, including our eyes, are susceptible to environment, age and the amount of time they have been active that day.</p>

<p>Here are two representations of the ranges, or gamut, of color devices. In the first shape shown below, the rounded outer shape represents the visible spectrum mentioned above; what we can see with our eye. The inner triangle shows device color. As you can see it is quite a bit smaller than the visible spectrum. The second image to the right is more device specific and shows the top and bottom of a 3D color model. The outer shape (white mesh shape) represents the color that a typical LCD monitor can produce.
<img src="/assets/images/spectrum3.png" alt="spectrum" class="avatar" /></p>

<p>The inner core (color shape) is what can be produced by a high-end printer. Once again, it is a much smaller, and you will notice that there are some
colors that can be produced in print that cannot be captured on a monitor.
<img src="/assets/images/spectrum2.png" alt="spectrum" /></p>

<h2 id="you-cant-always-trust-what-you-see">You Can’t Always Trust What You See</h2>
<p>One of the most shocking things I learned as an artist is that color has the illusion of energy and motion, and not just in the poetic sense. If you know how to harness this illusion, you can use it to great effect. If not, you can literally repel your viewers and can make text very difficult to read.</p>

<h2 id="vibrations">Vibrations</h2>
<p>Some colors vibrate when put next to other colors. In the chart below, you can see that, not only does it almost “hurt” to look at these colors, the text becomes very difficult to read without looking away. This is not something that you want your audience to experience.
<img src="/assets/images/vibration.png" alt="vibration" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/vangogh.png" alt="van gogh" class="avatar" /> 
However, this same effect is often used by artists to add energy to their paintings.
Notice how in Van Gogh’s Café Terrace, the artist uses the vibration of orange on the distant blue buildings to make the lights pop. Additionally, the yellow/orange colors
of the cafe push it forward and in front of the taller blue building behind it.</p>

<h2 id="contrast">Contrast</h2>
<p>Each color has their own value, or level of “greyness.” If the values of two colors are too close, like the example below, then the contrast is too low, with
“weak energy,” and can be difficult for someone with vision problems to see it. Again, there are many free contrast checking tools listed at the W3C.
<img src="/assets/images/contrast.png" alt="contrast" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Leigh Lawhon</name></author><category term="article" /><category term="Part" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This series of articles explains basic color theory. The first post explores color limitations.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Design Basics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/design-basics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Design Basics" /><published>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/design-basics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/2023/07/01/design-basics.html"><![CDATA[<p>Your brain has two systems, a slow analytical side and a quick, instinctive “gut” side. For the most part, the instinctual side is lazy, conserving its energy for the “pounce”. It doesn’t want to think or stop and read, it wants shortcuts, assumptions, and skimming. It is this part of the brain that design speaks directly to.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag002.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>To communicate with this part of your brain, design uses constructs such as motion, structure and even emotion, all without using a single word. Design is not just “what you like”, it is a language that is speaking to your instincts.</p>

<p>Look at the chart below. Can you guess what these symbols mean?</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag003.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>Some of these concepts maybe cultural, but most are pretty easy to guess.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag004.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>Let’s try another example, this one is in Japanese. Assuming you don’t know how to read Japanese, what can you tell me about this layout? Where is the title? What is it about (try and be specific). What does a callout look like? Where does the text begin?</p>

<p>More importantly, how do you know these things?</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag005.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<h2 id="what-gets-the-brains-attention">What gets the brains attention?</h2>
<p>In the next slides we will look at the language of design and how we can use it to direct our users to the more import parts of our interfaces. Let’s start with Distance.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag006.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>The slide you are looking at is flat. It’s two dimensional. But, can you tell me which object is in front? If you were to analyze it, probably not, but if you were to make a snap decision, you would probably guess the larger items were closer and therefore in front. Which of those items would your lazy brain care about? Well, if they were baseballs coming for your head, probably the closer one would get your attention. In general, things that are larger on the page and in front get more attention.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag007.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>What about balance? of these two sets, which is more interesting? Most people would say the one on the right is, but why? The two even blocks on the left are stable. They’re not going anywhere; the brain can relax. The three blocks on the left however not quite right. If they were cement, they wouldn’t stay in that formation for very long. The blocks on the right gain attention from the brain because a piece is missing and something may happen. As far as our lazy brain is concerned, odd things are more interesting than even.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag009.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>A similar thing happens with curved shapes instead over flat. The brain expects motion and gives those objects more attention.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag011.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>Value and contrast can also be used to focus the lazy brain. For the most part, easy to ready contrast is the goal for text, especially when it comes to text and 508 compliance. However, used sparingly, high and low contrasts can help structure your message.</p>

<p>Ansel Adams was a master manipulator of contrast. When I was young, I thought he was so “lucky” to find such beautiful spots and snap a photo at the right moment. In fact, he spent hours in the darkroom manipulating the balance in contrast to guide your eye. What path do you think your eye is taking across this photo? What do you think makes that happen (be specific)?</p>

<h2 id="composition">Composition</h2>
<p>We’ve seen a few examples of how to distinguish and separate ideas use the design language, now let’s look at how to bring ideas together using color and composition.</p>

<p>Color is one of the hardest design constructs to master. Most people, including “pre-art school” me, think about color in terms of what they “like” or based on the order of the rainbow. However, color has a complex structure, and all colors were not created equal. On the right you see color systems called color harmonies. One you might recognize from elementary school is complementary colors, or colors that are opposite each other on the color wheel. But do you know what a split complementary color is? Did you know that artists and designers use these color harmonies to create cohesive work? It’s what gives their work a polished look. However, without a single color theory course, you too can have a polished look. There are sites such as Colourlouvers.com and Adobe’s Kuler.com that are collections of color palettes to make working with color a breeze.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag012.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>The second thing developers need to know about color is that not every color can be represented by every device…but that is changing every day! In the bottom of the middle of the slide you see an illustration of several color gamut, or the range of colors different devices can display color. You may notice that the color you can display on your screen is much larger than what you can get off your printer, and the color your eye can capture is even larger.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag013.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>The Golden Ratio is a pretty interesting phenomenon. It can be found everywhere in nature and artist use it to create natural looking compositions. For the most part, developers don’t use this construct…with one really important exception. You will notice that the Fibonacci Sequence is part of the Golden Ratio, and though this may not affect the design decisions you make in your development, it is a good reminder that art and computer science are not that different.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag014.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>And speaking of compositions, did you know that most designers use a grid system to create those engaging layouts you see in magazines like the Japanese layout we saw earlier? Grid systems are not just for responsiveness. As we saw earlier, a well-structured layout can help you understand the flow of the document without ever reading a single word.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag015.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>Finally, let’s take a look at good typography. It’s an artform in itself. Think about all the ways we talked about to use design to separate items and bring them back together. What can you tell me about this image? Name all the different ways design is being used in these text-only images?</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag016.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>Two things you may not be aware of in typography are Kerning and Leading. Whereas kerning is the space between letters, leading is the space between lines. Do you remember what it was like to learn to read? Do you remember what your books looked like? Did they have more or less leading? Why do you think that was? What happens when you decrease or increase spacing between lines? What do you think your lazy brain would want?</p>

<p>All the tools I have just given you are all you need to practice good design. When you are sitting down to make an interface or even a presentation, think about what parts need to be emphasized and what parts should come first. Should a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">learn more</code> button be as attention getting as a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">donate now</code> button? Pick and choose what you want to give attention to. And remember…</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag017.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>…because if everything has attention, nothing has attention.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag018.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>My last tip is to think of you interfaces and presentations as welcoming a guest into your home. It should be focused and organized and have clear steps from beginning to end.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag019.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>

<p>Below are some recommended links to learn more about the concepts we discussed here:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/DesignBrownbag020.jpeg" alt="Design Brownbag slide" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Leigh Lawhon</name></author><category term="article" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This article explains basic design concepts that everyone should know.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LinkedIn Learning Courses</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/work/2023/07/01/linkedin.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LinkedIn Learning Courses" /><published>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/work/2023/07/01/linkedin</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/work/2023/07/01/linkedin.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="background">Background</h1>
<p>Since 2017, I have had the opportunity to build an tutorials for LinkedIn Learning. My projects aim to teach  concepts of JavaScript to beginner and intermediate developers, using narrative and project-based learning.</p>

<p>For each project, I developed (2-3 months) and the recorded the course (1 week).</p>

<h2 id="approach">Approach</h2>
<p>In all my courses, I strive to create a narrative that complements the learning objectives. By leveraging analogies, I am able to elucidate complex JavaScript concepts in a simplified and easily understandable format for learners.</p>

<h2 id="results">Results</h2>
<p>Upon publication, my courses have attracted many learners and have the following results:
<img src="/assets/images/LinkedIn_stats.png" alt="LinkedIn Stats" /></p>

<h2 id="next-steps">Next Steps</h2>
<p>I continue to develop how narrative-driven, project-based tutorials and explore the impact of story in education. You can find my latest course <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/learning/instructors/leigh-lawhon">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Leigh Lawhon</name></author><category term="work" /><category term="Tutorials" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This article showcases a tutorial that teaches learners how to code.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Packt Publishing Course</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/work/2023/07/01/packt.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Packt Publishing Course" /><published>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T17:13:27-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/work/2023/07/01/packt</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/work/2023/07/01/packt.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="background">Background</h1>
<p>In 2018, I designed and devloped a tutorial that teaches learners how to create motion graphics in Adobe After Effects.</p>

<p>The course can be found here: <a href="https://www.packtpub.com/en-us/product/getting-started-with-adobe-after-effects-cc-2019-9781838986841">After Effects 2019</a></p>

<h2 id="results">Results</h2>
<p>Upon publication, my courses have attracted many learners and have the following results:
<img src="/assets/images/Packt_royalties.png" alt="LinkedIn Stats" /></p>

<h2 id="next-steps">Next Steps</h2>
<p>I continue to develop how narrative-driven, project-based tutorials and explore the impact of story in education.</p>]]></content><author><name>Leigh Lawhon</name></author><category term="work" /><category term="Tutorials" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This article showcases a tutorial that teaches how to create motion graphics in After Effects.]]></summary></entry></feed>